[Music]
here to talk about the last the last
days on earth while I was looking over
this book this morning and it's a
beautiful it's a beautiful kind of epic
poem is it what she wrote called last
days on earth and it's probably much
more poignant right now because we're in
a kind of apocalyptic moment right yeah
so I should say that you're a poet
you've you've published quite a number
of books won all kinds of awards for
your poetry and of course that's not not
what matters what matters is is you know
the quality of what what you do which is
I think there's a there's a there's a
real let's say dedication and beauty and
profundity to your work so and in my
circles I don't know very many poets I
mean I haven't I
I've known poets in the past but I've
been talking to a lot of intellectuals
philosophers people who are very you
know very articulate in the intellectual
realm but I've also noticed a big gap in
in this scene and and I'm and I'm
wondering where are the poets and I'm
also wondering if this Cova nineteen
business somehow makes poet poetry more
important and you eluded kind of to the
prophetic aspect of poetry I think when
you said that you know you wrote this in
2015 and a poet has a sense of what's
happening around the corner and I've
been recently talking to Zack Stein and
genre Vicky about the prophetic aspect
of the arts and how they're very
important and how we need that in and
how that might be even more valuable on
some in some sense than you know the the
intellectual our the sociological or the
let's say the propositional political
etc
diagnosis of what of what's happening
now which is all very important and of
course all these realms are important
but but the one thing that's missing
maybe is this aspect of poetry and I'm
hoping that's going to change and I'm
hoping that you can speak to that a
little bit yeah the importance of poetry
yeah I would be happy to do that
um first of all I wouldn't make this
separation between philosophy and poetry
and politics I'm - to me it's always
been part of of the of the mesh and the
job of the poet is the root of poet is
to make and and so what poets do is we
make articulations of condition and so
we're using language and languages
already
a broken technology it's a it's a it's a
system of interrelated symbols that are
sort of mapped over a broken ontology so
it's an epistemological complex that we
think in and and language is how we
represent the world to ourselves and
then we directly weave begin to respond
to our own representations and so if
language gets stuck and if language gets
codified in a flag which gets made into
some official verse culture then our
thinking and our being gets stuck and so
the job of the poet is really to keep
language fresh there to come out with
new articulations of condition and in
and the idea is to have a place that we
could build together you know like I
always say if I write something that you
know it's boring to you if I write
something that I know it's boring to me
and so what I try to do is open up and
write something that that we could
explore together and make meaning and
make sense together you know it's it's
more of a democratic process right well
so there's a communal aspect right hello
to poetry which is very important which
perhaps gets lost in a culture of
entertainment or a culture of you know
individual egos sort of you know I've
noticed that in a slam poetry world it's
often a performance right it's very
performative and it's it's but often
that lets say that the depth is lost in
that and it's also about individual egos
you know yeah so so I think we I think
the poets are you know the poet's who
are valuable or a meaningful are deeper
than that right yeah yeah well I hope so
now you know there's this there's a
difference between you know a
performance right and and really a deep
poetic explorations and and there's
there's nothing wrong I have no problem
with what slam poets are you know yeah
yeah you know that's that that's all
well and fine
what's the content I think that I'm
criticizing there yeah the content it
can be somewhat either overtly pull it
to me it become it's politicized and
that it loses something and all or else
it's it's it's it's just biographical
yeah it's a narcissistic on one level or
it's it's some kind of ideology
ideological you know some kind of you
know expression of ideological
possession yeah but then but then the
poets the poets that are valuable to me
are not you know a political there is a
politics there but it's it's something
more radical and deep do you agree with
out of my yeah I absolutely agree with
that you know in fact in in in thinking
about this conversation because you and
I spoke and we had planned this I
brought a few things to read to
demonstrate you know probably that point
that you were just saying so you know
what I would I'd like to agree it is
just like a one page thing that I was a
contemplation on on what poetry does
towards agreement an agreement towards a
peacemaking and in
way of of coming into into alignment
between between people so in and I'm
reading this not as not as a discourse
an intellectual discourse but as a
demonstration of how to use language in
a different way so I'll read this and
then you know go for it awesome okay all
right so poetry or a language is the
playground we're invited to explore to
Prague the open space and poke into
difficult corners a hide-and-seek where
I see you and meet me we rock
stomp roll through minor sandbox like
disputes
it's my shovel it's my pail and stumble
headlong into resolutions whose will is
imposed whose questions are posed who
has the poise to resist insist in rest
composed but what is agreement other
than the problem of other minds never
mind
is it only trust in that meeting that
the other understands stands on the same
ground resound in the echoing of idea -
idea is it in the text or the context
and how do we prevent that from becoming
conflict a flick of a glimmer of a light
at the outskirts of darkened halls or
hallowed meanings to interpret or
interrupt what rupture is permanent what
rapture is persistent who brings the
ball and who gets to dance what singing
is the slinging of words into space the
matter of our time is it a sign or
symbol an empty cypher splendid symphony
what reference remains without referee
was it in or out in front of or behind
the line it's your call
or a fall or a failure forgotten in the
instant of instant reply all for one and
one for all out efforts to bridge the
budge this impossible distance into
something other than the in-between of
yes and no what have you erases me what
race is run what is one what is the
affected or is it broader the borders
that's seeking to divide can they not
only cleave into two but to frame and
inside where no one is left out words in
the air or flares cannons or treaties
words attempt to paper the resolution
understood beyond the temptation of
further thought ass waging the
difference over which all is fought what
is sought other than the residence were
once stood offense rock solid or folk
rock additional chant or techno rant
what is wrapped in the wraps brung in
the tuning of note to note two notices
of changing in the timing Accord perhaps
offers an accord the vibration ringing
in the resonance of yes in two we sing
but to get there they're crossing over
to agreement do we only agree in our
minds the internal belief about what the
other means is the same as we understand
understood to stand together under the
same cloud of language and hear the
resonating hum of yes the end of thought
is the beginning of agreement where
language let's go you begin a groundless
ground on the shore of some sea where
one is not a float but drifting sure
sure sure because it's such a surprise
right
I also the two words that that stuck out
to me when I thought I kept hearing
actually there was three I wrap sure and
rupture and and also there's there's a
strong musical metaphor in there
somewhere which I you know I'd have to
hear it again but but I think I think
it's the musicality of language mmm
that that I that I felt there that he
were that we that you were trying to
sing language rather that you know that
that it's it's the hearts language or
rather than again rather than just
remaining on the inside but at the same
time it's it's it's it's it's full of
thoughts and ideas and you know so it's
a it's a whole it goes in and out of
propositional into into into the world
and and then back into the mind and into
the heart and all over the place like
like a kind of like like again it's a
it's a form of jazz or something yeah
yeah and you know it's that that's a
Sennacherib the description in and you
fumble around trying to say well okay
that let me try to make sense of this
and what you just read means this and in
all my all my poetry exists that you
know and because you know again it's not
something that I'm saying you know
propositional e yeah you know it's
rather I want to create that space for
us to explore together and could you
create something together you know and
and that's what our does art art really
helps helps helps you move away from you
that move away from there from the ego
move away from from just the thinking
and in in really opens of space you know
a Fisher a crack a crime that you could
you could get you could get through to
something a bit deeper mmm at least
that's the intention
yeah and I imagine if if somebody else
was hearing you read this poem they
would they might get a completely
different dimension of it than I got you
know I got stuck on certain words
because that's was where I was at at
that moment that's exactly right
that's I was thinking of rupture and
rapture of those two words because
because of this feeling you know there's
this feeling at the moment of this sort
of rupture of the ordinary like
everything going kind of weird and then
there's also a kind of coming into being
of something else which is ecstatic so
it's just suffering an ecstasy meeting
or or something like that right does
that make any sense when I guess yeah
absolutely it does and and you know the
the the poetry that I try to produce
either helps a reader get to that space
or process through that space or that
allows allows a field okay a field that
the play in to explore you know and it's
not saying that what I do is wide open
you know every every every work I do has
has an intention and an intention or a
thought or an idea you know the way I
like to describe it is like you know if
we're playing in the playground you know
and you could imagine you know I have
kids and and when the kids go to the
playground they all do different things
you know and and so their experience of
the playground is going to be totally
different from from one another however
they all could agree that they were in
the same playground mm-hmm so there's a
form to it as what you're saying it's
not just total formless free jazz it's
right there's there's there is a form
and yeah and also I think that that's an
interesting analogy because I think that
you know we're not and again this is
what I was talking about with John John
and Zach or what they were saying is it
this atomized individual we're not just
one thing right right all kinds of
different personalities and
subpersonalities within us and they make
up a kind of chaotic symphony of sorts
and so so of different types and
archetypes and personalities and stuff
and they're all in this playground
uh-huh experimenting and trying to work
together and coming in and out of
harmony and and collapsing
yeah yeah and you know that that's that
that's it and you know it's you know
it's kind of funny when I think about it
I mean I've written a bunch of books and
every book every project is radically
different from the one that went before
it which is a really bad career move but
but I mean that's how how how the poetry
it's a bad career move because people
want you to be a certain thing that's
exactly right and and when you
disappoint them they reminds me of Bob
Dylan a little bit of like you know what
it was I was changing and people are
always reacting to that and in a
negative way every time he changed
something about himself but he was
always sort of a step ahead of of the
time he was always just a little bit
ahead of the time yeah yeah yeah yeah
and but it's that exploration and it
said that allowing to to come through
what what that time is just becoming so
like every time I write a a book I
learned from it you know if it's not
teaching me something then then I'm
probably wrong hmm yeah I understand
that that's right yeah cuz cuz if you if
you know where you're going when you're
writing a poem it's not going to be a
poem no it's just going to be a
regurgitation of what you already know
so the poem has to be breaking into new
ground for yourself you have to be
hearing something ahead of you
right hey well exactly oh yeah you're
hearing your divine double I know that's
speak to you mmm that's good waiter yeah
that well that is exactly it you know
when you're writing a poem or you're
creating any part of any sort of art
it's already there right so it's like
we're talking about time before time
doesn't really exist I mean it's the
perception of duration and then
certainly your relation to you to where
you are at that moment and when when
you're doing a creative project like
when I have when I'm working on a book
you know I'm just well the beginning of
that project is always just waiting okay
so I just wait
until I send something and then and then
it's about following it through so you
know I'll get you in a place where you
know I'll hear usually it's a vibration
or a sound you know so the musicality is
extremely important
it doesn't start in language if it
starts in language I know I'm thinking
about something and I'd rather write an
essay or do CrossFit
it's not that so where does it start and
a feeling of discomfort or or ecstasy or
what what it where does the feeling what
is the feeling where does a poem start
yeah it starts in a feeling yeah and
it's just that you know it's it's an
embodied sensing you know in in it's not
it has no no no qualities that I could
ascribe to it I can't say it's gonna be
happier sigh other joyful or any of that
but it's a feeling you know it's almost
like a whole whole vibration and and
then you know some words will come and
then I'll sense into that and it's like
okay
and it's always out there just just that
ahead and I try to follow it the best I
can and and what's really funny in that
process is because you're collapsing
time and and you're also you also sense
when you have it right you know and so
it's an art of really feeling your way
through yeah you know if it if it like
if it feels wrong it's probably it's
probably dead weight or it's probably
not essential or it's probably mm-hmm
yeah yeah and it's it's that the process
is really about a tuning into that and
you know like all my books I don't have
it you know I just I was gonna ask you
about that actually I was gonna ask you
about that so you don't edit at all no
because I so you work like Jack Herer
kind of just like a you know you let it
all go out or or well you know there
must be some preparation or some
well the preparation is really sitting
in in being with that that thing that
wants to be expressed and and in really
doing a practice to get into a space
where you're ready to receive if you
will and and so what and it's oftentimes
nothing comes out you know with Kerouac
and you know those guys who are doing
you know stream of conscious whatever it
all comes out and then there's an
editing or not sure for me it's it's
about waiting it's about you know
pulling the hand backs like you know
that's not it that's not it and then
when I sense that it's right it just it
just comes out and that means so if
you're saying that's not it aren't you
editing a little bit in your mind I'm
trying to get I'm trying to I get get
around and get to this idea of not
editing cuz it's exactly the opposite of
how I work I I just go over stuff over
and over again until it till I get to
something essential I mean and I write
songs right so long has to be it has to
be a bullet it has to have all or it has
to be a complete thing i if there's if
there's you know where's it where's I
think a poem you have much more room and
space to explore you have a larger space
to explore it perhaps than a psalm where
you have to if you fit yourself into
some kind of form and I find the form
kind of freeing or I kind of find the
limitations freeing and I find that
perhaps I don't trust myself enough to
not edit yeah wait you know you're
bringing up a really interesting point
and this is what I spoke a little bit
about at the conference you and I were
at where we met in he back in September
and and there is a meta move that
happens in that process
and in the the meta move is that you see
yourself writing you know so so there's
a there's a perspective that has the
sense and when I say see that's probably
too strong but that there's an awareness
of what you're doing and
that you're you're right the editing
happens in that meta level and that's
where I'm saying no you know that's
where I can pull it back if I see that
or fight sense that that it's not
following that the trajectory of the
future thing that wants to come in so
there's a dialogue that goes all right
before it before the poem comes into
being so there's a dialogical process
perhaps we could have to look at it that
way
rehearsal because I felt like I felt
like when you were reading the poem to
me actually I felt like that you were
going through a dialogue with yourself
with different aspects of yourself yeah
well for that it was specifically around
an agreement you know so so that the
concept was agreement and in and how do
we how do we agree yeah ie in conflict
or prevent conflict and and what is that
what is the language is role in that and
you know in the the dialogue is also
part of the problem cuz it's - and I'm
not interested in - I'm interested in
three you know the the the two is really
the the epistemological roots of the
technology of language okay well three
is interesting as three is like there's
the dialogue between you and whatever
element your dialogue you against and
then there's a third thing a third
element right now which is the spirit of
the whole thing you could call if the
logo sir we were calling it the logos or
something like that which is which is
actually the third element like I agree
if it's just a dialogue of just back and
forth
there's no inspiration there's there's
just where there might be a rivalry or
there might be agreement but but it's
the third part that gives you the this
inspiration right right you know and it
comes back to you know just just our own
psychology or makeup is you know
language begins when you could say I
write and and at that point you have
separation and so I is contradicting
instinct from the knot I so you're into
that that duality yeah and and that is
the problem and you need the vow that I
and there's the that's the third element
like I'm thinking of boobers formulation
yeah there's the I in the it now but
then there's a space in between which is
the vow you know or you know for me it's
more it's more Buddhist I think you know
in it it's the the non-dualistic dualism
that that makes the third for me so so
it is it is the I and the not I that are
that become held in a non-dualistic
dualism they exist but you don't see
them apart from from one another and not
that dualism hmm yeah it's not not a
negation right it's not an aggregation
nourifusion it is holding it's holding
the the the the this is the ability that
that they had to live in the paradox
okay of the not knowing if that space of
not knowing knowing he you know in and
this is where it gets really difficult
to articulate something using language
that has the the the the goal to
articulate something that's beyond
language and you know that's that's
that's poetry you know and that's music
and that's art that's that's that it
takes you to to a different a different
space hmm so you are objecting to that
vow in the sense because it's it's too
much of a let's say theistic concept or
something like that no it's a it's the
it's the separation that that I have a
problem with mm-hmm yeah the dualism the
dualism that that that that forms the
epistemology I mean if we're thinking in
language and language it's beast is is a
technology of but doesn't the vow allow
you to transcend do dualism in the sense
it's no longer me versus you it's this
it's it's it's the relationship like
like our friend Nora Bateson speaks
about a lot huh yeah yeah the
relationship of everything to everything
else you know that the it's the
complexity Nora would say you know in
the ecosystems that the complex
ecosystems in relation to each other in
a mutual learning and and say that's the
Norris Norris main point is that the is
is that the complexities are always
continuing to learn and and and they're
adjusting in relation to everything that
being everything that goes on and in in
in poetry I you know that is like the
the piece I read which is sort of a
poetic essay is really an attempt of
creating a complex ecosystem of thought
you know thought of feeling of
musicality of breaking through that
separation so that you could enter in
and and and be in in relationship to it
hmm that makes me think that there's a
hospitality that is necessary here
there's you have to invite people into a
space which is hospitable in some sense
but also challenging and that which
makes you you know grow and learn yeah
well you know it to me it's about it's
about did the democracy of the page you
know in it's about participation and
this is you know I often get labeled as
experimental and there's a whole group
of us cut from the 70s 80s 90s and still
continuing who who are essentially left
out or we're really resisted by you know
what we'll call official burst culture
there's a mechanism that you don't want
this kind of disruptive thought poetry
in in the world or in the academy
because they're you know it's it's
controlled it's controlled by by the
Academy by the publishers and so a lot
of us had to go yeah it's kind of a blue
Church of poetry exactly so to speak
yeah exactly
you know sort of mmm yeah right right
and and there's there's you know there's
a more or less a suppression or you know
trying to to keep out you know these
this sort of this sort of thinking
because it is it's just very disruptive
you know I don't because if if you if I
can't tell you or if you can't if you
can't say what a poem means or have some
status because you understand what the
poem means and somebody else doesn't
this is why you know when people hear
poetry they think they go cold because
because they've been trained that that
poetry has the secret message and only
very smart and bright well-educated
people huh yet it you say no and then
what we're saying is no no no no I mean
you know we have a strong theoretical
base and that we operate from but the
poetry is you said is is in an inviting
place it's a place it's a place for
trust build community come together mmm
great great okay
can you read another poem Joe okay well
I will read a poem so there's a little
bit different than than the the poetic
essay and I still think that was a poem
but I appreciate that I like to think
everything I write is a call all right
exit wound there is nothing left to
build but only to tear down desire and
repeat it if a crane could the Rope
would not be enough such as pitchers
frozen by the frame they're part of a
world at the outside of need an earnest
act of necessity could not make it
pretty and so to see still swells its
calling and who to die run skip the
imagery of wonder a branch has turned to
fruit at the outskirts of
last thing and leaves us here the
thought has been caught out cleans fly
lights on wheels extended to the
approaching and its own spent not to use
the last of the tower is quite a task
the desk man waits behind his counter of
redemption will a breeze come it can't
be built but descriptions are all around
go grab hold the hammer ground into sand
hmm yeah that's definitely a poem we
agree so so so congratulations and it's
not because I understand it but but
because I follow it it's it's unusual
logic or it's it's radical logic right
right because I understand what you're
saying it's because it's purely
evocative and but but you know it's it's
like it's like um a dream or something
or it's not quite right anyway I don't
really know what to say like it's hard
to say what I said too to say something
after after hearing a poem well I do I
say um I would hope so
I would I would hope so you know the the
poem yeah here's my impression of it and
it's yours is equally valid you know
just because you know that I put it on
paper doesn't mean I own it you know so
yeah I was thinking of the exit wound
you know so hugs it named his name of it
um so and that always comes last
um is how what what what what what's the
price of getting through what's the
price of exiting thought you know how do
we do that you know in this align you
know the thought has been thought out
you know cuz he you can you can oh that
deadline struck me - yeah the thought
has been thought out yeah and it's been
all around right you know it's like
everybody you
and at the end of at the end of
philosophy at the end of science at the
end of any any deep any deep dive on any
particular topic you're gonna come to
this place where you can't think it
through anymore
and and there's that's because there's a
different type of knowing there and and
that knowing is very resistant to
articulation and and poetry's job is to
try to articulate that you know can't be
articulated exactly exactly there's a
paradox always at the heart of it yeah
well there is the paradox and you know
it's like Keats said right you know the
there's there's the the ability of a
poet to have the negative capability to
exist and be comfortable in the not
knowing in in the unknown and and that's
very frustrating for a lot of people and
especially for especially in Western
culture you know where you know where
where we've just been reductionist and
scientific and you know we divide
something and study it and have have a
you know have an understanding of it and
then you know and it's broadside it's
brought us a great deal it's compromise
everything we see around us but at a
cost then and the cost is the
environment and and and and a
relationship to one another right and so
the cost is our the the poetic aspect of
our relationship perhaps or at least the
rich aspect of our relationship as
opposed to the let's say utilitarian or
[Music]
instrumental and aspect we have a
relationship so we see things in we see
things in we're always always we see we
always see things as as as thinking
about Heidegger ESA's standing reserves
or us as resources for us or or as and
then we missed the whole richness of the
in-between of the liminal of the
of the of the ever-present creativity
which is just happening right right and
and you know it's moving from from a
transactional based relation to yeah
accumulation right so we don't want
transaction we want the relation then
and to be in a relationship one to
another is is is difficult you know it's
Nikita because the as you said before
the individual holds multitude and in to
stay in relationship and individuals and
very complex ecosystem and and in dude
for two of us that come into relation is
there's always challenge you know so it
gets really easy you know they have a
transaction it's like okay I'm gonna pay
you to wash my car yeah it's like yeah
you know and that's or are you know you
put Joe into this category Joe the poet
so I know what I know what to expect
from Joe because Raisa
he's a poet right whereas somebody else
I know what to expect from them because
yeah yeah yeah so you know that's that's
part of the the you know my my project
and I hate using the that's sort of
language but it's been the thing that
I've been interested in since forever
is you know I started out in science I
was gonna be a doctor sighs really in
the hardcore sciences yeah and you know
around the time of university that I
realized at the endpoint of science is
going to be to disprove itself because
if the premise is a hold on you know you
can only cut things up so so much and
that reductionist point is not going to
be useful at some at some point now yeah
and and so okay so what do you do you
know so how do you bring the whole back
how do you bring a whole back into you
to residents in in a community then in
that that that's that's the project so I
started meeting series started group
projects you know just just get into a
conversation with with artists other
poets you know people
we're thinking like this and you know so
we invented just out of necessity a way
of reading you know traditional you know
money and and whatnot
by that I mean it's always been in
relation and giving so every time I meet
and it still happens with any poet
friends you know what we do is we swap
books right and and we share and and
because we have a network globally you
know yeah I can I could go to just about
any major city and find a poet there and
and have have instant community and then
reading a place to stay you know so you
know it's a it's a different orientation
do you think artists poets at Citra are
a vulnerable community right now well
yes and no right that's a hard one
venerable he yes certainly because we
hope we always are you know because we
we don't we don't fall into that
traditional way because we put we put
our energy into this creative act which
entails a sacrifice of often material
comforts or or or job status or whatever
it might be
well that's it it you know it's it's
vulnerable only from the sense of of of
societal expectations and the means of
making a living now now it's also very
resilient because at this moment you
know yeah you know it's hard to say but
but this really isn't being on lockdown
isn't really any that much different
than my normal day-to-day you know and
and that's always been about you know be
trying to do the creative and going in
and and in doing
deep introspection and all not all that
that a lot of people at this moment are
are having I would imagine a very
difficult time well people are freaking
out perhaps because they've been living
in a transactional world and they're not
getting the feedback they're used to now
so they're stuck with themselves yep and
in worse than that they've defined
themselves in relation to externals you
know they they are their job they are
there they know there's there's spot on
this fourteen that I don't know so yeah
it's I think there's a there's a lot of
pain out there right now certainly that
it hurts me and I feel that deeply but
that gives me another insight to why the
the poet is is kind of important right
now and that is that that in the modern
society we have a narrow vision of what
a person is and the poet opens up a
portal where we can see that the person
is to something much larger and much
more mysterious and must let much less
atomistic and much more of a symphony of
voices yeah yeah and and and also that
that that goes for for every individual
yeah so the individual has to give
themselves the permission to say didn't
see themselves and that fed multitude
mmm you know and at that point you know
it's not vulnerable all its it's it's
very rich it's incredibly rich yeah but
it's a process sure and so that the poet
you know the poet say sorry to interrupt
go ahead continue here this case a poet
said you know in society that are
undergoing change like let's say
political change often get rounded up
you know because the poets are dangerous
yeah you were I was just about to bring
that up the idea of danger you had one
of your questions was why are the poets
and artists artists dangerous and and
it's because they they break the
the rules of the current exactly norms
right and which is a threat to people
but if they're responsible poets right
they're they're offering a different a
new vision of the world right so so it's
not that just that they're tearing and
tearing the it down yeah well you know I
don't think poets tear down
um I think the danger you're you're
close but the way I would read that is
opponents are dangerous because they
allow the society and see the repressive
mechanisms and that's what the power
thing that be don't want and and so
that's that's that's danger that's why
there's this kind of hatred towards the
poet or something there's hatred towards
this type of person who is not it was
nonlinear who has you know might might
appear to be crazy at times might might
not be easily categorizable or
understandable you know all right
and you probably know being in poetic
circles that you know I think artistic
people in general are sensitive and they
often they have substance problems or
certain mental illness problems or they
tend to fall into a lot of they tend to
they tend to you know go into dangerous
territories psychological territories
and sometimes they they make it and
sometimes they don't
yes yes there did this you probably
known a few people like that and yeah
well you know I thought I wouldn't rule
myself out you know because when you're
in in that process I mean you've what I
mean you're still here on writing poetry
and you're still you're still going but
I think a lot of people you know are
casualties yeah yeah well you know III
think that goes through it for artists
you know I or any any sensitive
individual you know let's say we could
say an artist as a person with some
kind of poetic capacity yeah they're if
they're really an artist so poetry is is
one written poetry is one aspect of that
but yeah not exactly exactly and you
know and I wouldn't even make the
categorical distinction between poet and
visual artists the musician and
architect and you know yeah or or you
could do anything in life artistically
sure you know again that's one of the
traps isn't it the specialness to put
there you go oh yeah I'm special so poor
you know you could say that that are
that may be the meaning of life is just
to meet it as artfully as possible then
as you can and it doesn't have to be
some specialized art work or art form or
art yeah yeah I would agree with that
you know and and part of like that the
flipside of the danger part is you know
that people don't want to hear or
sometimes want to prohibit the the veil
from being lifted and society at whole
and so that they counter-attack to that
is like oh well she's just a poet he's
just a musician and and it's like
they're a fool yeah he's so you you try
to make them into into a clown or a fool
and and it's it's it's a trick of yeah
well we see it in politics all the time
of authoritarian control it's like the
first the first the first thing
everybody was saying about Trump let's
say because I'm American is that well
he's a buffoon he's a fool and that's
very dangerous
because then then then he you know
you're allowed to to do so many things
that and and be ridiculed of and and in
in the meantime they're they're they're
taking taking down the structures you
know so yeah that's the white language
is very very important
you've got to keep language fresh and
you know and it's a living thing and
you've got to renew it you've otherwise
you get stale yeah and you start bumping
up the two-year-old representations and
because they're familiar you say oh okay
I know I know this script yeah yeah and
it seems that we're exposed to so much
language noise these days oh yeah
because of social media and because
everybody has a voice so there's this
cacophony mm-hmm
so so I would say I would say the people
who have real a real poetic aptitude or
whatever the artists you know it really
need to go into nature or go into
meditation or or go away get go offline
and you know get it get out of the the
you know the endless the endless noise
and the attack of noise and and and you
have to you have to learn to listen
don't you - oh yeah you have to you have
to listen deeply to something other than
the noise of the collective super-ego I
can call it that yeah or the whatever
you know I just you you go on Facebook
sometimes and you're like Jesus Christ
it's like it's like this it's it's
everybody's subhuman gossip just being
demonstrated in mm anyway yes no I I
agree you know I find you know language
is absolutely exhausting to me language
exhausts me you know I don't I'm happy
not to speak most of the day you know so
so this is this is where I had to have a
conversation like this you know because
it is this taxing um and it's also to
try to talk about this is something that
they resist the the articulation is
reaches a limit and and you could only
you can only surpass that or or show it
by going into into the art itself
you know and III social media yeah
absolutely it's toxic everybody knows
that and you know so I try to use like
Facebook like right now during this this
crisis time and I'm just putting up like
a poem thought it's it's not a poem it's
not a thought it's like just something
that's coming through and sharing it and
again the idea there is just a build
community you know and to have something
to where people could just slow down and
breathe for a moment yeah but do you
ever feel like you're you're you're
throwing your pearls to swine and in a
sense like like there's this companies
that are making money off of people's
you know emotions and feelings and you
know yeah you know I'm absolutely not
naive you know and about about media
companies base workers in social media
I'm there it's really there
you know it's cannibalism you know there
is a good word for it you know yeah
that's really what they're doing it's
consuming consciousness
exactly exactly it's consuming other
people's consciousness it's like the
ultimate zombie or something right busy
brains they take the consume
consciousness right right you know so
I'm well aware of that
and at the same time there's an
altruistic compassionate act of like
just getting somebody who you know falls
on something that I wrote a place of
respite of quietude of reflection I was
like okay no not not everybody is like
this against us so the poem is an oasis
of some sort in I'm a desert of in a
digital desert so in some way yeah I
hope so
you know music in painting you know
although they are it's great it's a wee
something that brings an individual back
to the recognition of their own key
nominee
and the inter connection and the inter
being of all of us
that is important now more than ever
because as we go through this crisis you
know you know it's cliche to say we're
either we all get through it together
none of us do
but it but it's true nonetheless no and
in any way you know regardless of that
you know then the bigger context it's
about how do you want to live your life
I mean you want a high present I want to
put say you know floral but I want to
live my life in relation in the
tribulation relationship with others and
and and and all all o being know it's
why why would you want to live in a in
the separation by data mm-hmm
I never missed a better what about well
I kind of wanted eyes interesting you
were saying that that that we want to
get back to something like some more
sane you know a community based society
with genuine relationships rather than
transactional ones etc and then we also
talked about the prophetic aspect of
poetry about seeing what's happening in
the future and you know I've been
thinking a lot about that what is the
prophetic and the more I think about it
the more I think that you know strong
poetry has it as a prophetic aspect to
it would you agree with that a if it
does it's it's like your book it seems
to be somewhat prophetic at least and
it's like
because you keep saying this is left and
you you describe the world to fragments
right all this is what is enough but
also the there's there's like an ecstasy
in a trauma happening at the same time
as the trauma and ecstasy happening at
the same time as you're going through
this landscape of all these neglected
forgotten broken things of TS Eliot
wastelander or whatever whatever and I
said at the same time embracing them
more you know when I picked up your book
and started reading it I had the sense
that there was a prophetic quality to it
yeah perhaps but you wouldn't want to
perhaps own that or
what of what I would say is I didn't
know it at the moment
you know I sensed enter this is 2015
yeah you know so I sensed that something
was coming no you know said since that
book I've done to others so it's like
you know is that good is that predictive
of time coming I don't know you know
we'll we'll see but but I do I don't
know if I mean that predicting in turn
okay know that I think that's too much
of a reductive idea of what I mean by
prophetic okay uh-huh that's fair
yeah prophetic you know there's also the
sense of prophecy in that in and to me
prophesy lands on intentionality and and
if to the extent that we're going to
create a future we have to have some
vision or intentionality of something to
come that we do we live into that yeah
so so in that sense yes I would own that
the prophecy because that that part is
always aspirational it's like okay there
there there's this current and you know
we can you could do but the prophetic is
also coming to terms with the grief yes
and the tragedy of this moment yes so we
have to do this first yes before we get
to what what what does that cause the
post tragic or the the next world or or
you know
world you know we're leaning into her
imagining or dreaming of right right
that makes sense
you know it certainly and and it's
really frustrating when when people when
I hear people saying well this moment is
I'm very grateful for and it's it's
gonna bring us to our senses and oh yeah
it's gruesome
yeah because it's a denial of of the
grieving process a very deep breathing
process that that has to be has to be
experienced and I mean you cannot
sugarcoat that at all I mean we they're
probably the best thing everybody could
do is that to go deeply into that and
sit with that that's that's the only way
you're gonna release the shadows of it
even and and it comes almost like
there's no there's no choice at this
point it's not like a decision to do
that right it's just it's just that it's
it's in our face right you me even if
we're sitting watching Netflix 24 hours
a day we're still the truth of what's
happening the death all around us is
going to have some you know effect on
our consciousness certainly hmm yeah
yeah yeah yeah and and our own potential
you know you know death right I mean I'm
I'm I'm only I'm not quite 50 years old
I have some gray hairs you know I'm not
you know this this thing could take me
out could take you out on a ways we have
to think about that right and and and we
don't want to think about that but we
have no choice to think about that right
now which is interesting
yeah it is you know now I'll tell you
you know at the beginning of this and
wow like in January way before the block
down I have friends in China so I saw
tonight okay I saw was who's coming and
and also from you know my my scientific
background I knew severity that was
likely to hit
and and at the point of loves lockdown
here in France mid March is the the
realization that my parents are in their
80s it's like I mean never seen them
again and that's very real and and I
allowed myself to to process really sad
with that as a is a very real
possibility and and in and through that
process to extend it out to you to all
of humanity that we're all going through
this then you know so you not not make
your heroic sense it's like oh okay well
he's great good for him
no it's that you know you look located
personally and and I think the the
artistic sensibility is to to feel into
what what's going on I said that a
species level yeah again and that's
another reason why maybe poetry is
important right now because we are
confronted with our own mortality
yeah and what do we want to hear on our
deathbed or you know we don't we don't
care about our you know the you know our
job or you know as much or a role or you
know there are you know what we're
trying to achieve or that kind of thing
we we need the essential the essentials
right and a poetry is sort of aiming
towards the essentials I think yeah it's
also the play you know it's just the
richness of life that we want that we
need to that we contemplate much more
deeply when we're faced with the
possibility of deaths right yes
certainly I mean you know existential
crisis brings it brings it really close
and and I'm you know this this brings it
home to everyone because it's like like
you said yeah it could be literally
brings it home yeah you could do me it
could be you um in in that sense of the
immediacy brings people to you
to to a different sort of sense yeah
yeah it's not it's not like like climate
you know good the climate crisis you
know it's that's it's it's hard for
somebody to to experience that how much
you're a farmer or a myelination where
you see it
most people that doesn't affect and so
it's hard to get traction yeah
interesting but this thing is much more
immediate amaze essential on an
existential level then than any one of
these other sort of hypothetical threats
or idea that it even if they're real
they're just they don't the reason we
don't change you know our habits to to
fix the climate is because we don't
really feel that it's a reality on a
somatic level like there's no
existential threat there right right
right now right right always but but but
but now here we have an existential
threat that's happening right now on
some level you know even if that
existential start is already there I
mean people die and there's tragedy
happening all the time it's not like you
know there's no there's a bit more of it
happening right now but yeah you know
what I mean it yeah and in it it also it
also impacts everybody I mean well you
know you and I I mean we live
15 minutes apart but here we are you
know yeah so we can't do this in person
can't do this in person but we can we
can send our trumpet out in Torah bar
you know we can trumpet it out into the
Internet's ether you see and see where
it lands and people it lands on and and
hopefully we're not adding to the noise
I don't think so well I think I think
they I think the long-form discussion if
people have made it to this point in the
conversation yeah and if there if
there's that kind of engagement Oh
either people won't listen because they
don't have the attention span or if they
go this far
they got me to this far in the
conversation then then they're they're
probably part of the conversation and
the conversation is expanding and it's a
deep conversation and that's a long-form
conversation like it's like reading a
book or or as opposed to just watching a
soundbite yeah well that you know that
that's it it's like that's why I do this
I mean well you know thank you for doing
this has the been serious and that the
conversations you're having or you know
very very important you know if they
saved my sanity a lot you and you know
in our little network of podcasters it's
it's it's it's very very important and
it's also it's also an important work
it's well I'm hoping it as you say I
hope it is genuinely community building
on some level I think it is I think it's
very I think it's really generative um
you know in at this stage it's it's
generative in the sense that these these
different sorts of conversations are
going out in the communities going to
collect coalesce around around bits and
pieces of this I don't know how we all
come back together again and what we're
going to do but certainly we know that
we're not alone and that there's people
that we respect that are giving some
deep thought and working on on the
situation that we find ourselves in and
in this this this goes from you know pre
coronavirus right pre Cova time mm-hmm I
mean it's really important it's like it
does but this Kovan thing is an
intensification and a deepening and it
just really feels that way it's an
accelerator so I think it's an extremis
it's a it's really accelerating
whatever's happening positive negative
yeah you know you don't have to even
have a judgement on it but something but
it's just deepening and acceleration
over present
individual sister or president you know
self I know when use wear itself but are
present you know local situation but
also and also magnified in the in the
world situation yeah I think that's
right and you know it's like a it's like
when when I write a book right you know
a book gets published right and you know
I write it and I think you know I you
know there it is even suddenly a
publisher takes it and there it goes
it's out in the world I have no idea
I have no idea who's wears it where
where it's landing if it's touching
anybody or if it's yeah if it's landing
nowhere I don't know but what I do know
that it's it's taking part of the the
the sphere of the poetry so it's
contributing then you know and maybe the
future is going to look like something
where where we can connect at the
community level we have to rebuild
smaller units and more more
earth-friendly resilient sustainable
ways and at the same time we're like you
like you say where we aren't going to
connect like this yeah
so I think it's both the local and the
global and whatever noticed in this
conversation is that it's sort of
blending into other conversations that
I've had like there's a unity forming in
all of these conversations so it's not
just me talking to you it's it's we're
speaking and then I'm bringing in the
other conversations that I've been
having with people and so so the
conversation is becoming larger and more
and it's taking not not an absolute form
but it's taking some kind of let's say I
think
it's it's it's it's taking this kind of
a form of some sort not I'm not a fixed
form but a moving form yeah yeah you
know it's it's it's really in the
process of building itself of becoming
of emerging and in we don't know I think
you know that's that's that's the the
humbling form any position that they may
find themselves injured you know one of
the first times is that we really don't
know and and when was that ever not the
case you know so you know maybe we fool
ourselves into into thinking that we do
know and we can control but that this is
a reminder of the hubris of all that and
and and it's it's a call to to reconnect
what what what's really meaningful and
most important mmm maybe you can read
another poem at this point speaking of
what's meaningful and what's important
oh that's a no pressure right I don't
mean to butter you up here well this
that this works in light of the
conversation I'm in line
not knowing is the best state and
privilege to be the head of it a road
map not to be followed is what the guide
said what is eternal is transfigured so
the book says take the nearest stairs
and wrestle with them is what I said for
fear of being beneath wait this
heaviness of yes when this heaviness of
no we divided the loaf in half and
exactly half we're left out
this is invention this is fable when
asked
[Music]